A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17 FA289
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
1960-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA289
2.89 Cubic Feet 7 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement note
The Finance Committee Series contains four subseries.
Subseries 1 Budget Statements for Board of Directors Meetings
Subseries 2 Carleton B. Chapman Files
Subseries 3 Chemical Bank Monthly Statements of Investments
Subseries 4 Finance Committee Meetings
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: budgets, correspondence, and meeting minutes.
Child welfare; Education, Rural; Child mental health; Child psychology; Legal issues; Legal research; Hygiene; Law; War relief; United States; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Public welfare; Public health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Medical education; Mental health; Harkness, Charles W.; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Columbia University; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harvard University; Yale University; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Social Science Research Council
- Budget Statements for Board of Directors Meetings, 1960-1980; 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The Commonwealth Fund Board of Directors meetings are held in February, May and November of each year. For the meetings of 1978 and 1979, the minutes and dockets of the Board of Directors meetings themselves are included with the budget statements. This subseries spans February 1960 through February 1980.
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Budget Statements, 1960-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Budget Statements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Budget Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Budget Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Budget Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Budget Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Budget Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Carleton B. Chapman Files, 2
  This subseries includes financial material from Commonwealth Fund President Carleton B. Chapman's files that was kept distinct from his records in Series 2: Administration - Officers.
  - Budgets, Cash Flow Charts, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - CF Funding for Experiments in Health Care Delivery, 1964-1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Financial Statements, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Memoranda, 1974-1976; September-October, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - President's Statement for CF Annual Report, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - President's Statement for CF Annual Report, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - President's Statement for CF Annual Report, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - President's Statement for CF Annual Report, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - President's Statement for CF Annual Report, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - President's Statement for CF Annual Report, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - State of the Fund (Carleton B. Chapman Report), November 1978 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Chemical Bank Monthly Statements of Investments, 3
  This subseries contains monthly reports issued by Chemical Bank regarding the Commonwealth Fund's endowment and investments.
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Monthly Statements, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Monthly Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Monthly Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Monthly Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Monthly Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Monthly Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Finance Committee Meetings, 4
  This subseries includes the minutes of the Finance Committee meetings.
  - Minutes, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Minutes, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Minutes, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Minutes, 1977-1980 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Minutes (and Reports to the Directors), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Minutes (and Reports to the Directors), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Minutes (and Reports to the Directors), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Minutes (and Reports to the Directors), 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 62)